Guide to the New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry Records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry Records,
1768-1984
(bulk 1860-1973).
New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry.
185 linear ft. (337 document boxes, 81 oversize bound volumes, 50 bound publications, 17 flat boxes, 1 index card box 1 small flat box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
6621724
MS#1440
These records document the history of the New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry, beginning with its establishment in 1768. Tracking the wax and wane of the organization's influence over the next two centuries, the collection provides a first hand account of the Chamber's many contributions to New York City and State business and development. These records exist in a wide variety of formats, such as bulletins, correspondence, minute books, and printed materials.
Historical Note
The New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry, founded in 1768 by twenty New York City merchants, was one of the first commercial organizations of its kind in the country. Formed around the premise of serving the needs of the local business community, the Chamber eventually became one of the industry's strongest advocates. Over the years, its activities attracted the participation of a number of New York's most renowned business leaders, including former New York City Mayor and the Chamber's first president, John Cruger, Samuel F.B. Morse, John Jacob Astor, Peter Cooper, J. Pierpont Morgan, and multiple members of the Vanderbilt, Rockefeller, and Murray families; notable figures such as Thomas Edison, Andrew Mellon, and Herbert Hoover were elected to honorary membership. The Chamber aimed to unify the voice of commercial industry in New York, allowing a respected forum for dialogue among its members which would often result in an amalgamated effort towards action and resolution. The prominence and power of its members garnered distinction for the organization, placing the Chamber in a unique position to command the attention of government bodies both locally and nationally. Collectively, the organization was able to agitate for legislation that would provide a favorable climate for the growth of business in New York City and State, in turn encouraging the development of a complex urban environment in which commercial industry could thrive.
The Chamber's founding members first met on April 5, 1768 at Bolton and Sigel's Tavern, now known as Fraunces Tavern, to form a mercantile union that would defend and promote their collective interests. Organized under the name the New York Chamber of Commerce, the society moved its home base to the Royal Exchange in 1770, and was granted a royal charter from King George III incorporating it as “the Corporation of the Chamber of Commerce in the City of New York in America."
At the outbreak of the American Revolutionary War, the membership was divided into Loyalist and Patriot factions. Patriot members, including John Cruger, the first President of the Chamber, left New York City after the British invasion of 1776 while their Loyalist counterparts continued to hold meetings and transact business in the City. After the British evacuation in 1783, the Chamber's returning Patriot members quickly established control over the organization and relocated to the Merchants' Coffee House building. The Chamber was issued a new charter in 1784 reincorporating it as "the Corporation of the Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York." In 1793, the Chamber again relocated; this time to the Tontine Association across the street from the Merchants' Coffee House. Member participation began dropping steadily after the turn of the century, and by 1806 meetings were suspended due to lack of attendance.
In 1817, Chamber President Cornelius Ray called for resumption of the organization's business. New officers were elected and the membership base was increased by thirty-six during the first meeting. This marked the beginning of a new era for the organization. As of 1827, the Chamber had claimed the Merchants Exchange Building as its headquarters; however, the Great Fire of New York in 1835 forced members to relocate once more, this time to the Merchants Bank on Wall Street. Though many of the Chamber's prized historical objects and documents were saved from the fire, including member portraits, minute books, and the Chamber's official seal, the original charter is believed to have perished.
By 1849, membership had surpassed the two hundred mark, and the administration became increasingly consumed by management concerns. Elected officers authorized the hiring of an official clerk and librarian to assist the elected Secretary in overseeing day-to-day functions. The administrative staff was vital to the operation of the Chamber, answering outside inquiries on the organization's work and fielding appeals for guidance and counsel from commercial organizations across the country, all the while facilitating dialogue among the Chamber's constituency and countless committees. The outreach efforts of the administration, in addition to the prestigious projects the organization was involved in, quickly established the Chamber as a model for other chambers of commerce, both domestically and abroad.
As its membership increased in size and prestige during the 1800s, the Chamber's power grew accordingly and the organization proved to be instrumental in the realization of several initiatives integral to the development of both New York City and State. In the interest of serving regional commerce, the Chamber heavily promoted the construction of the Erie Canal in the early 1800s and the establishment of the first transatlantic cable in 1858. The Chamber became progressively more involved in trade and commercial concerns at the national and international levels, and began releasing annual reports in the mid-1800s which outlined the condition of mercantile affairs and noted important changes relative to trade in the national business market. Perhaps one of its most recognized contributions to the business industry was its role in arbitrating commercial disputes among regional merchants. The Chamber's creation of a Court of Arbitration, a body recognized by the State to oversee commercial disputes, and its own Committee on Arbitration, whose records and purpose often overlap with the Court's, are both indications of the Chamber's commitment to settling mercantile disagreements and furthering its goal of providing merchants with an agreeable environment in which to conduct business.
The Chamber also lent its support to major public works within New York City--the expansion of the City's water and waste management system, construction of a rapid transit system, and quality commercial education for area businessmen were all projects championed by the Chamber. The defense and management of New York ports and harbors were also of concern; the eruption of the Civil War in the United States prompted the Chamber to gather funds and successfully petition both the Executive and Legislative branches of the United States, the New York State Legislature, and the New York City Council for an allocation of money for the defense of the New York Harbor. In addition to these large scale ventures, the organization was involved in numerous smaller projects over the years, including construction of a lighthouse in Martinique, overseeing the Nautical School of the Port of New York, and developing measures to protect the City's population during cholera outbreaks in the 1890s.
Many of these accomplishments can be attributed to the work of the Chamber's standing committees which began to appear in great numbers by the second half of the 19th century. Committees were an essential component of the organization; they allowed members to focus on a broad range of issues relevant to commercial industry in the New York region and nationwide. Standing committees often concentrated on a general sector of commerce such as finance, conservation, public service, or taxation laws, while ad hoc special and sub-committees focused on these topics in finer detail. The proliferation of committees at various points in the Chamber's history can be directly linked to contemporary affairs; certainly, the occurrence of particular events throughout the 19th and 20th centuries, such as debates on the National Budget, natural disasters, or urban entertainments, can often be traced by the existence of corresponding Chamber committees.
At the turn of the 20th century, the Chamber's administration grew again as it faced a progressively more complex business environment; the administration now included the elected positions of Executive Vice President, Assistant Secretary, and Assistant Treasurer. The result of the Chamber's growing influence and prosperity was the 1902 completion of construction of the Chamber of Commerce building at 65 Liberty Street in lower Manhattan. Illustrating the Chamber's importance at the national level, both President Theodore Roosevelt and former President Grover Cleveland spoke at the building's dedication. The top floor of the new building, the Grand Hall, was lined with the Chamber's collection of over 200 member portraits and it was here that most business was transacted, including regularly occurring member meetings. The Chamber's wealth and prestige continued to swell exponentially, and in honor of the Chamber's significant projects and influential membership, increasingly opulent annual banquets were held. Invitations were delivered by messenger and hand engraved by Tiffany and Company, whose founder was also a member.
Following this period of economic and civic prosperity leading up to the 1920s, the Chamber began a gentle descent, slowly losing members and influence. The Chamber began considering the possibility of merging with other New York City commercial organizations as early as the 1940s. An agreement was reached in 1973 between the Chamber and the Commerce and Industry Association, formerly the Merchants' Association, to merge the two parties into one organization: The New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry. However, this new incarnation of the Chamber did little to alleviate the organization's declining revenue and dwindling authority. In 1979 the Chamber left its headquarters at 65 Liberty Street and moved in with the New York City Partnership, an affiliate organization founded by Chamber member, David Rockefeller. In 2002 the two organizations formally merged to form the Partnership for New York City and the Chamber ceased to exist.
Scope and Content
The archival records of the New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry provide a thorough history of the organization, rendering a vivid portrait of the Chamber by means of committee records, minute books, printed materials, photographs, reports, and a wealth of correspondence. Materials originate mostly from the 19th and 20th centuries, though there are some notable items from the 18th century such as the first volume of Chamber of Commerce meeting minutes that dates back to 1768. Subject matter in the collection primarily focuses on New York City and State commercial and urban development, though it often extends to national and global business concerns. This collection is particularly notable because of the presence of the records of the Commerce and Industry Association, formerly the Merchants' Association, a commercial institution whose focus and constituency were comparable to that of the Chamber. The Chamber of Commerce merged with the Commerce and Industry Association in 1973 and thereby acquired the Association's historical records. Series IV is devoted solely to the records of the Commerce and Industry Association while the remaining nine series are divided according to format or purpose.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in ten series.
Series I: Administration, 1866-1980
Series II: Annual Reports, 1858-1975
Series III: Bulletins, 1909-1970
Series IV: Commerce and Industry Association, 1873-1978
Subseries IV.1: Administration, 1935-1973
Subseries IV.2: Bulletins, 1901-1976
Subseries IV.3: Committees, 1906-1978
Subseries IV.4: Correspondence, 1923-1974
Subseries IV.5: Meeting Minutes, 1897-1973
Subseries IV.6: Printed Materials, 1873-1973
Series V: Committee on Arbitration, 1820s-1973
Subseries V.1: Arbitration Cases, 1820s-1973
Subseries V.2: Case Correspondence, 1914-1930
Subseries V.3: Chairman's Files, 1865-1967
Series VI: Committees, 1822-1973
Subseries VI.1: Administrative Committees, 1864-1973
Subseries VI.2: General Committees, 1822-1973
Series VII: Correspondence, 1804-1984
Subseries VII.1: Administration Correspondence, 1859-1984
Subseries VII.2: Gwynne, Charles, 1916-1941
Subseries VII.3: Subject Files, 1804-1979
Series VIII: Member Meeting Minutes, 1768-1973
Series IX: Printed Materials, 1774-1977
Series X: Photographs, 1860-1980
Subjects
Commerce and Industry Association of New York.; Court of Arbitration (New York Chamber of Commerce).; Hundred Year Association of New York.; Merchants' Association of New York.; New York Chamber of Commerce.; New York Chamber of Commerce.--Committee on Arbitration.; New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry.; New York City Partnership.; Partnership for New York City.; Port of New York Authority.; Sailors' Snug Harbor (Institution).; Bernheimer, Charles L. (Charles Leopold), 1964-1944.; Bush, Irving T., 1869-1948.; Cohen, Julius Henry, b. 1873.; Cruger, John, 1710-1791.; Rockefeller family.; Great Britain--Colonies--America--History--18th century.; New York Harbor (N.Y. and N.J.).; New York (N.Y.).; New York (N.Y.)--Commerce--History--18th century.; New York (N.Y.)--Commerce--History--19th century.; New York (N.Y.)--Commerce--History--20th century.; New York (N.Y.)--History.; New York (State).; New York (State)--History.; United States--Commerce--Law and legislation.; Arbitration and award--United States--Cases.; Boards of Trade.; City Planning--New York (State)--New York.; City Planning--New York Metropolitan Area.; Commerce International.; Commerce associations.; Industries--New York (State)--New York.; International commerce and arbitration.; International commercial arbitration.; Interstate commerce--United States.; Merchants--New York (State)--NewYork--History--18th century.; Transatlantic cables.; Transportation--New York (State)--New York.; Usury laws--New York (State).; Usury laws--United States.; Addresses.; Annual reports.; Architectural Drawings (visual works).; Autograph Albums.; Business Records.; Bylaws.; Case Files.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Deeds.; Invitations.; Leases.; Membership lists.; Memorial works.; Menus.; Minutes.; Pamphlets.; Photographic Prints.; Press Releases.; Programs.; Reports.; Scrapbooks.; Slides (photographs).; Visitors' books.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
York City Partnership, Gift 2002 (material was physically transferred in 2004. Additional transfers were made in 2005 and 2006).
Related Material
New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry Publications Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Columbia University.
http://www.columbia.edu/cu/libraries/inside/projects/findingaids/scans/pdfs/NYCCPublications.pdf">
Related Material
New York Chamber of Commerce Building Architectural records 1901-1966, Avery Architectural and Fine Arts Library, Columbia University.
http://www.columbia.edu/cu/lweb/archival/collections/ldpd_7084607/index.html
Related Material
The New York Chamber of Commerce Portrait Collection, New York State Museum
http://www.nysm.nysed.gov/research_collections/collections/history/nycc/"
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Administration, 1866-1980
  The first series of the collection offers materials that reflect the administrative tasks of the organization. Because the subject matter is broad in scope, the series has been divided into small sections with each section heading arranged alphabetically. Records related to financial matters, the construction of the Chamber of Commerce building in lower Manhattan, and public relations materials such as press releases and printed distribution materials can be found in this series. Also present are the records of the Board of Trustees of the Real Estate, a designated group of Chamber members who dealt primarily with the property holdings of the Chamber; various affiliate organizations who shared membership with the Chamber and often maintained offices in the Chamber of Commerce building; and of particular significance, documents that detail the Chamber's eventual merger with the Commerce and Industry Association in 1973. Items related to the events hosted by the Chamber are especially rich—records of the Chamber's annual banquets, New York public school essay contests, and various luncheons and receptions honoring prestigious figures can be found here. This series also offers a few items of realia, notably several medals created especially for the Chamber of Commerce to commemorate specific accomplishments.
  - General
    - 100th Anniversary of the Inauguration of George Washington--Scrapbook, 1938 (Box 392, Folder 2)
    - Action Program for the ‘70s, 1970 (Box 373, Folder 1)
    - Archival Project, 1979-1982 (Box 373, Folder 2)
    - Archival Project--Inventory, 1966-1984 (Box 373, Folder 3)
    - Commissioner of Pilots--Election, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Famous Signatures, 1869-1883 (Box 373, Folder 4)
    - George Washington Statue, 1881-1883 (Box 271, Folder 7)
    - History of the New York Chamber of Commerce, 1960-1968 (Box 374, Folder 6)
    - Members in the Service, undated (Box 271, Folder 8)
    - Membership
      - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1943 (Box 373, Folder 5)
      - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1948 (Box 373, Folder 6)
      - Rockefeller, John D., Jr., 1950-1954 (Box 373, Folder 7)
    - Memorials in Manuscript
      - 1869-1875 (bound volume) (Box 437)
      - 1875-1880 (bound volume) (Box 438)
      - 1883-1906 (bound volume) (Box 439)
    - Military Service Records, 1918 (4 Folders) (Box 373, Folder 8 to 11)
    - New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry Day, 1973 (Box 392, Folder 1)
    - New York Port Treaty, 1920-1921 (Box 373, Folder 12)
    - Other Chambers of Commerce, 1960s (Box 374, Folder 1)
    - Papers Relating to Wrecks on the Bahama Banks
      - 1859 (bound volume) (Box 437)
      - 1860 (bound volume) (Box 435)
    - Petition to Congress from Citizens of New York for Postal Reform, 1856 (bound volume) (Box 436)
    - Purchase of the Site for the United States Post Office, 1869 (scroll) (Box 376)
    - Stainback, Thomas--A New Look at the Assets of New York City, undated (Box 271, Folder 9)
    - Statistics on Vision, 1915-1920 (Box 374, Folder 2)
    - Subway Fares, 1947 (Box 374, Folder 3)
    - Unemployed Ex-Service Men in New York, 1922 (Box 374, Folder 4)
    - Visitors/Guest Book
      - 1860-1930 (bound volume) (Box 429)
      - 1904-1940 (bound volume) (Box 430)
      - 1939-1965 (bound volume) (Box 431)
      - 1965-1968 (bound volume) (Box 432)
      - 1966-1976 (bound volume) (Box 443)
  - Affiliations
    - Citizens Committee for New York City, Inc.--Starting a Merchants Association, undated (Box 328, Folder 1)
    - Citizens Committee of One Hundred--Teachers' Salaries, 1920 (Box 317, Folder 1)
    - Free Canal Union of New York, 1880-1884 (Box 317, Folder 2)
    - The Hundred Year Association of New York Administration
      - 1940s (Box 223, Folder 1)
      - 1950s (Box 223, Folder 2)
      - 1960s (Box 223, Folder 3)
      - 1970s (Box 223, Folder 4)
      - 1972-1979 (Box 223, Folder 5)
      - 1978 (Box 315, Folder 1)
    - Annual Dinner
      - 1954, (2 Folders) (Box 315, Folder 2-3)
      - 1955, (2 Folders) (Box 315, Folder 4-5)
      - 1956 (Box 315, Folder 6)
      - 1957, (2 Folders) (Box 316, Folder 1-2)
      - 1959 (Box 316, Folder 3)
      - 1960 (Box 316, Folder 4)
      - 1961 (Box 316, Folder 5)
      - 1964-1979 (Box 223, Folder 6)
      - 1966-1979 (Box 316, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1980 (Box 223, Folder 7)
    - Financial Statements, 1960s (Box 223, Folder 8)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1967-1977 (Box 223, Folder 9)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1978-1980 (Box 224, Folder 1)
    - Membership, 1976-1979 (Box 224, Folder 2)
    - Membership Correspondence, 1956-1962 (Box 316, Folder 7)
    - Membership Correspondence, 1956-1962 (Box 317, Folder 3)
    - National Port Week, 1979 (Box 224, Folder 3)
    - Official Documents, 1928-1949 (Box 224, Folder 4)
    - Press Releases and Newsletters, 1964-1978 (Box 224, Folder 5)
    - Scholarships and Awards, 1971-1979 (Box 224, Folder 6)
    - National Association of Export Management Companies
      - Minutes and Administrative Documents
        - 1964-1965 (Box 224, Folder 7)
        - 1966-1968 (Box 224, Folder 8)
        - 1968-1969 (Box 224, Folder 9)
    - New York-New Jersey Committee for a Self-Supporting Seaway
      - 1957-1958 (Box 317, Folder 4)
      - 1957-1960 (Box 317, Folder 5)
      - 1957-1961 (Box 317, Folder 6)
    - New York Port Promotion Association
      - General
        - 1965-1967 (Box 236, Folder 1)
        - 1967-1968 (Box 236, Folder 2)
        - 1967-1970, (3 Folders) (Box 236, Folder 3-5)
      - Art Contest, 1962 (Box 236, Folder 6)
      - Gwynne, John, 1967-1968 (Box 236, Folder 7)
      - Minutes, 1960-1963 (Box 236, Folder 8)
      - Minutes, 1964-1967 (Box 236, Folder 9)
      - "What the Port of New York Means to You" Leaflet, 1967 (Box 236, Folder 10)
      - Trustees of Sailors’ Snug Harbor, 1944-1946 (Box 374, Folder 5)
  - Board of the Trustees of the Real Estate
    - General, 1907-1924 (Box 327, Folder 1)
      - Building
        - 1897-1913 (Box 327, Folder 2)
        - 1901-1903 (Box 327, Folder 3)
        - 1905-1922 (Box 327, Folder 4)
      - Building Fund Bonds
        - Court Case, 1917-1918 (Box 327, Folder 5)
        - Inquiries, 1915-1921 (Box 327, Folder 6)
        - Surrender of Ownership, 1903-1929 (Box 327, Folder 7)
        - Surrender of Ownership, 1912-1938 (Box 327, Folder 8)
      - Lease
        - 1941-1943 (Box 328, Folder 2)
        - 1952-1971 (Box 328, Folder 3)
        - 1954-1967 (Box 328, Folder 4)
        - 1958 (Box 328, Folder 5)
      - Minutes
        - 1900-1936 (bound volume) (Box 440)
        - 1921-1922 (Box 328, Folder 6)
        - 1936-1958 (bound volume) (Box 441)
  - Building (65 Liberty Street)
    - Appraisal of Furnishings, 1926 (Box 318, Folder 1)
    - Contractor Contract, 1901 (Box 318, Folder 2)
    - Landmarks Preservation Commission, 1966-1973 (Box 318, Folder 3)
    - National Historic Landmark Designation, undated (Box 372, Folder 3)
    - Relocation Surveys, 1955-1980 (Box 318, Folder 4)
    - Renovations, 1947-1959 (Box 318, Folder 5)
    - Title and Deed to Property, 1899-1901 (Box 318, Folder 6)
  - Department of Transportation
    - Administrative
      - 1964-1973 (Box 320, Folder 1)
      - 1975 (Box 320, Folder 2)
      - 1976 (Box 320, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 320, Folder 4)
    - "The Impact of Containerization" Workshop, 1966 (Box 320, Folder 5)
    - New York Transportation Council
      - Agendas and Supporting Materials
        - 1968-1969 (Box 321, Folder 1)
        - 1971-1975 (Box 321, Folder 2)
      - Board Reports
        - 1958-1967 (Box 321, Folder 3)
        - 1968-1974 (Box 321, Folder 4)
      - Briefs and Petitions, 1973-1977 (Box 321, Folder 5)
      - Public Relations, 1964-1976 (Box 321, Folder 6)
    - Shippers' Conference of Greater New York
      - Bulletins
        - 1969-1971 (Box 322, Folder 1)
        - 1973 (Box 322, Folder 2)
        - 1975-1976 (Box 322, Folder 3)
      - Petitions